<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A more full answer of John Bastwick, Dr. of Phisick made to the former exceptions newly propounded by another wellwiller to him, against some expressions in his Letany, with his reasons for the printing of it. All set downe as more articles superadditionall vpon superadditionall, against the prelats. This is to follow the Letany as a fourth part of it.</title>
            <title>Litany. Part 4</title>
            <author>Bastwick, John, 1593-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05633</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104510</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840246</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840246</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4725</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05633)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4725)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 653:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A more full answer of John Bastwick, Dr. of Phisick made to the former exceptions newly propounded by another wellwiller to him, against some expressions in his Letany, with his reasons for the printing of it. All set downe as more articles superadditionall vpon superadditionall, against the prelats. This is to follow the Letany as a fourth part of it.</title>
                  <title>Litany. Part 4</title>
                  <author>Bastwick, John, 1593-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Willem Christiaens],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Leiden] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeare of the English prelats malice, and crualty, against and upon Gods faithfull people, 1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The fourth part, of the Letany of Iohn Bastwick, Doctor of Phisick.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bastwick, John, 1593-1654. --  Litany --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England. --  Controversial literature --  Puritan authors.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4725:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4725:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MORE FVLL ANSWER OF JOHN BASTWICK, D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> OF PHISICK, Made to the former exceptions newly propounded by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other wellwiller to him, againſt ſome expreſſions in his LETANY, with his reaſons for the printing of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All ſet downe as more Articles ſuperadditionall vpon ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>additionall, againſt the Prelats.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This is to follow the LETANY as a FOVRTH PART of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare of the Engliſh Prelats malice, and crualty, againſt and upon Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people, 1637.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4725:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4725:2"/>
            <head>The fourth part of the Letany, OF JOHN BASTWICK, Doctor of Phiſick.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>Vorthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS I moſt kindly thanke you, for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny favours, you ſhewed me in my proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſo I do heartily, for your well wiſhes towards mee in this my captivity: and as I do cordially thanke you for both, ſo I do likewiſe promiſe all reciprocall endeavour in all Offices of love in way of remuneration: and ſo much the more your humanity deſerves it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you condole not onely my preſent deſolation, but ſtudy to prevent further fury in my adverſaries, which will tend to my greater ruine as you ſay, if they have any juſt, or but ſeeming ground for it: and therefore you have freindly I thanke you adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed mee of ſome danger you feare will come upon mee, if my <hi>Letany</hi> ſhould be publiſhed, in regard of ſome expreſſions in it, as that I ſeeme to vilifie the Service of the Church eſtabliſhed in the Kingdome by Parlament, and that I <hi>call the Prelate of Canterbury VVilliam the Dragon, and his brrther of Yorke, the abby lub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the North;</hi> now they being privy Councellors, ſuch ſpeeches will be adjudged ſcandalous as you ſuppoſe, and therefore that I ſhall be cenſured for <hi>Scandalum Magnatum.</hi> And withall you thinke it is a revillng thoſe in authority, which the Angel would not doe to the very Devill. And this is the ſumme of what you have to object againſt my Letany. To all which although I haue formerly anſwered in my let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to others, yet becauſe I know not whether you may ever ſee them, I thought fit in breife to reply as followeth.</p>
            <p>And firſt whereas you ſeeme to intimate by your words, that I ſhould either totally ſuppreſſe the printing of my LETANY, or els take out thoſe words: I conceive neither of both by any ſound reaſon ought to be done: for that the LETANY is printed, <hi>the Prelats are the cauſe of it:</hi> and of the writing of it: for would they have let mee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed my owne imployments, I ſhould never have troubled my thoughts about them: for I moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly confeſſe unto you, that nothing more greeves mee, the that I am conſtrained to make thoſe men a ſubject of my diſcourſe, that at other times I would ſcorne to make an object of my cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: but they I ſay, having by their unhuman and unchriſtian proceedings <hi>deprived mee of liberty, and all lively hood, and</hi> by this meanes <hi>ruined mee and all mine, and to all this threatned farther calamity and miſery unto mee,</hi> as the <hi>ſlitting of my noſe, the branding mee in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> &amp; the <hi>cutting of my eares,</hi> all which things being dayly related unto mee by others, I muſt confeſſe it, put me upon my devotions, and was the onely cauſe of my Letany; and had not their thundering words come unto mee, I ſhould never have done any thing in Engliſh: but that my country men, might ſee ſomething into the Prelats well meaning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Church and State, and withall might be ſtirred up to a diligent, endeavour to prevent the miſcheif, <hi>as they feare God, and honour their King and lowe their religion and country,</hi> I writ that treatiſe, and ſent it to my good Angel, but hearing withall, that ſome evill Angells were abroad, and had miſinter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted it, and the Prelats threatned me yet more cruelly for that: then I reſolved to make that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick which otherwiſe ſhould have been for my owne uſe, and the benefit of ſome few frends onely: and this is one of the cauſes of the printing of it, and all my other ſuperadditionall articles againſt them: For at the making of it, I had never thought to have lived a day: the plague on every ſide envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roning mee about, and many <hi>poore people coming up to my chamber for cure with ſoares running on them:</hi> all the Phyſicians being gone out of towne: and therefore my danger being ſo great, and all poſſibility of eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of it, being alſo taken away, I tooke my ſelf then to my Letany, and that it ſeemeth was not well taken by M. Preiſts &amp; Prelats; neither could they conceale their venome, and evill intents, but muſt for the greater terror of others divulge them, and they as I ſaid coming frequently to my intelligence, for feare withall, that they ſhould adulterate my true copy, I therefore writ over another with my owne hand which I got to be copyed out, and ſo let ſome of my freinds ſee it, and ſuch alſo as had been many yeares in the High Commiſſion Court, and that knew very well I ſlandered them in nothing I ſaid: onely out of their good affection towards mee, they feared, and that very much, that the Prelats would proceed to the extremeſt and rigerouſeſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that by law could be inflicted upon mee. For <hi>their Kingdome was firſt by bloud begun and eſtablished,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4725:3"/>and by bloud hath hitherto been continued, and by bloud onely shall be perpetuated, but for my bloud and life I ſtand not for that, ſo that the truth may be knowne, and their wickednes, plots, and cruelty be diſcovered,</hi> and truely next unto the eſpeciall providence of God, which all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes bringeth good out of evill, I may thank the Prelats for the honour of this good worke (coſt it mee what it will) for they onely were the cauſe both of the beginning and publiſhing of it: for if they had not breathed out threats againſt mee, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaging their bloudthirſtineſſe, I ſhould never have ſtudied to dive ſo far into this buſineſſe; in the which through Gods bleſſing I have made ſo good progreſſe, as I hope all thoſe that either, feare God or their King, or love their countries, through the whole Chriſtian world, with all the <hi>Christian Kings, Princes and Emperors, and all free States will manifeſtly ſee, not onely the little need of the Prelats Government in their Kingdomes and Countries, but the great miſcheife and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage they bring to all Common-Wealths and Nations where they dwell.</hi> And to ſay no more but the verity, there is as little need of them, and their juriſdictions in Kingdoms for the well adminiſtring of them, as is in our Chriſtian and holy profeſſion of the <hi>Service-booke, which yet never either begot grace or the feare or love of God, or increaſed any gift of God in any;</hi> and is well knowne to the whole corporation of thoſe that call upon the name of God in ſincerity, that it doth not onely hinder goodnes, but doth hurt, and that abundantly, &amp; indeed were there no other juſt cauſe of caſting of it out, but that it doth no good, this I ſay were enough to remove it: but eſpecially when it is a cauſe of much evill every way, it ought to ſtirre up authority to looke into it: for very reaſon tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth us, that which is no way uſefull nor needfull for the ſalvation of men of that there can be no true need: now of the Service booke there is no need nor neceſſity, for if there had been God would him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe have appointed one, and all Chriſtian Churches would have had that, that had been needfull to their ſalvation: and therefore, when God hath neither appointed certain prayers to be daily read, nor other Chriſtian Churches which are daily ſaved, never had any: and when no man dare conclude that any man was ever excluded from heaven that never heard any Divine ſervice, it ſeemeth a ſtrange thing to mee, that ſuch a peece of ſervice in our Church ſhould be authorized that was taken out of the Maſſe booke; and of the which all the learned in reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches where I have lived, wonder that ſuch a learned Prince as King Iames was, would ever admit it in his dominions; for they all had ſeene it, it being tranſlated into French, and this I was often an eare witnes of that the profoundeſt men ſaid, if ſo be they had a purpoſe to turne againe to Babylon, from which they were commanded to come out, they would for a ſpeedy way bring in the Engliſh ſervice and diſcipline; and then farewell immediatly all true religion and the intire ſervice of God, and by this meanes they ſhould give ſo great and ſtrong a weapen into their adverſaries hands, as they ſhould never be able to make good their proceeding, and withall ſhould in a little time breed ſuch a deale of ignorance in the people, as they would be eaſily ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced. For whereas many of them, had not time through their many occaſions in the whole weeke to reade the Scriptures, if they ſhould alſo on the Lords day be taken up in reading of prayers gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and collected out of Popiſh Pamphlets, this would bee an abſolute meanes to extinguiſh that little knowledge they had already, and bring in blindnes in ſtead of it. And with all the correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency that was between them in rites, Ceremonies, and Service, would kindle a greater love in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts to their ſuperſtitious worſhip, and in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant it would alſo upon the leaſt occaſion beget ſome deſire to returne unto their old errors: and therefore they proteſted as they tendered the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, the ſalvation of the people, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of learning, they could never admit of our ſervice amongſt them: of all which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed they thought it an enimy, and they add far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that if they had ever beleeved that ſuch formes of prayer had been for the advancement of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, and the glory of God, and the edification of the people, they had thouſands in their Church that could make formes of prayer, and never be behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Maſſe-booke for them.</p>
            <p>And I can truely ſay thus much, I neuer yet met a Miniſter in France, were hee in neuer ſo meane a place, but he was a diligenr preacher, and able to inſtruct any flock, withall he was of ſo good litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as I never ſaw yet Biſhop, or any high Prieſt in England to be compared to him for that, which I ſpeake to the eternall honour of that people, that giue vnto their Miniſters ſuch ſingular breeding, and haue ſuch care in their elections that they be able and ſufficient men, and euery way ſo accompliſhed for life &amp; doctrine, as they cannot neither by feare, fauour or preferment be brought from their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, nor by all perſecutions, warres, bloudy maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres be in the leaſt daunted or deterred from their holy profeſſion. And of this Chriſtianimity is this people and many more, and of this ſound learning, where they neuer had a Letany or ſeruice book: or either in gouernment, diſcipline, or ceremonyes, were like vnto the Papiſts, all which haue been euer dangerous if not fatall to all true religion: for when Chriſtians began to bring in Iewiſh and heatheniſh ceremonies, rites, and cuſtomes, and their inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they then began to pervert true Religion and corrupt the ſound doctrine of our glorious and holy profeſſion. And King Iames himſelf though for ſome ends, he was willing for a time to retayne the ceremonyes, yet he profeſſed in the conference at Hampton Court, that if he did dwell among the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4725:3"/>heathens &amp; Papiſts that then there was great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in ſymbolizing with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any ſuch things, for it would much animate them in their ſuperſtition, by which they might be hindred rather then furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in religion: but in regard that they had no Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts among them which might be hurt by them, he was the more willing to conniue at them, but had he liued vntill now, and ſeene what miſcheif both ceremonyes and ſervice haue done amongſt vs, or did but King Charles ſee, or were but truly informed of the ignorance that is amongſt the people both in regard of their duty towards God and his royall Maieſtie, of the backſliding to Popery and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which hath ever proteſted againſt, he would take ſome ſpeedy courſe for the remouing of all the occaſions of it which is nothing els bur the ſeruice booke and ceremonyes, with their corrupt diſcipline &amp; Gouerners, &amp; as by his autority &amp; the autority of his royall Predeceſſors they were eſtabliſhed, ſo when the inconueniences of all ſuch conſtitutions are by dayly experience ſeene, which was euer ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cauſe to abrogat lawes, and diſmiſſe Officers, they may well be remoued with the great good to the whole Church and ſtate and to his excellencyes immortall honour and the perpetuation of his Crowne and dignity. And thus much at this time ſhall ſuffice to haue ſpoken concerning the ſeruice book and the tackling belonging to that buſineſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue formerly ſpoken of it.</p>
            <p>And now I am come to your maſter and capitall exception, where you thinke that they will heauily cenſure mee for calling the Prelat of Canterbury <hi>William the Dragon</hi> and the Biſhop of yorke <hi>the abby lubber of the North.</hi> Which you coniecture will be eſteemed <hi>ſcandalum magnatum</hi> and will cauſe a ſeuere puniſhment from autority, and which they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo cruelly threatned vnto mee for the ſame words, and therefore you would haue them omitted. But before I come to the diſtinct anſwer to that you now ſuggeſt, I thinke it fit to ſay ſomething for a proeme concerning this <hi>ſcandalum magnatum,</hi> and the orginall of it you very well know, that Kings haue euer been called and eſteemed Gods vpon earth, and they indeed went before their people ſhining in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and goodnes, of which they were compoſed, &amp; ſo farre they were from any commaculation of vice, that people were not to thinke euill of the King in their bedchamber, or to ſay what doſt thou? by all which is ſufficiently inferred, what excellency is in Princes and mighty potentates aboue other men. And as Kings had the ſupreme and firſt degree of dignity both for place and vertue: ſo next vnto them, had the true Nobility and great Heroes their ſtation, whoſe firſt riſe to honours was their wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and true ſeruice vnto their Prince and good they did to their country, according to that of the heathen, <hi>fundamentum nobilitatis vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt.</hi> So that the true and antient Nobility were ſuch as next vnto their Kings and Princes were for all excellent endowments ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly qualified, as they were not capable of any aſperſion, and if any had been ſo black mouthed as to haue layd any blemiſh vpon their reputation, the euill alwaies returned vnto themſelues, neither was their honour impeached by it, but rather il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated, for the whole world was well acquainted with their goodneſſe. ſo that their traducers, were branded for calumniators amongſt the people, which was puniſhment enough and eternall ſhame vnto them. And ſo ſarre were thoſe truly heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Spirits from making any lawes about ſuch a thing that they neuer thought ſo poorely of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as that any could ſpeake the leaſt thing to their infamy by which they could wound their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations and vertuous life, And the ſame good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe yet dwelleth in all the ancient Nobility and ſuch as are truely illuſtrious and magnates, ſo that they are like their Kings and Maſters whoſe digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty no blaſt of a foule mouth can contaminate among the really vertuous and heroicall: and ſo conſcious they are to themſelues, of their excellent integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that they will not ſo much as ſully their thoughts with what any clamorous tongue ſaith, much leſſe their eſtimation among the prudent, as to make them ſuppoſe that they are moued with railings which hurt them no more then the dogs barking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Moone. Notwithſtanding ſince thoſe antient and truely honoured Nobility, there haue ſprung vp a new generation of Lords, who fearing the calumnies of the vulgar, as new Lords are a meanes of ſounding new lawes, haue obtained ſo much of prudent Princes and Kings who were wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to yeild vnto their weakenes that ſuch lawes ſhould be enacted, but with no intent that the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſuch men ſhould be ſmothered, or that thoſe ſhould be puniſhed, that were detectors and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſters of them, but onely for both terror and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment if they had vnworthily defamed their noble families out of their priuat malitious and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courous minds; neither doth the eminency of place in any ſubiect warrant him ſecurely, to doe any thing againſt the honour of his King and Maſter, or the moleſtation of his Kingdome and ſubiects, or is the meaneſt ſubiect to be puniſhed for doing his duty in this kind, for the dignities conferred vpom them in ſuch proximity vnto the King, is ſo much the greater tye vnto them for the due hounouring of their Prince, and ſeeing that next vnto him, whoſe place it is to protect his people they ſhould add their helping hands in ſeeking the ſafety and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of them, and be indeed mediators betweene the King and the poore people, if they had fayled by frailty in their duty and loyalty to his Highnes. Now I ſay when all thoſe that are dignifyed with honours, do neither truly honour the King as they ſhould, and are ſo farre from making a ſweet har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4725:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:4725:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4725:5"/>between the King and his people, as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually rather put into his royall heart ſiniſter opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions againſt his beſt ſubjects, and traduce their beſt endeavours, &amp; pervert their words to contrary mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and make their poore brother a prey for a word, as the Prophet I ſay ſpeaketh, and do not onely move the King againſt them, but do in their owne perſons, and by the authority that they have given them, tyrannically abuſe the ſubject to their utter ruine and undoing, all ſuch I ſay are ſo farre from having any priviledge by the Law, as they themſelves are delinquents in a high degree of contumacy by ſuch demeanour, and are fallen from their dignity. Neither do I conceive that any King or people can take it ill at the meaneſt ſubjects hand for diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any ſuch mens practices, when I ſay, they are ſo prejudiciall to the State. In the number of which men, to ſay nothing neither of the obſcurity of their parentage, the meaneſſe and the poverty of their breeding, the beginning of their order, and whoſe image they are, the uſurpation of their places, being by them the ſworne rebells of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and the curſed enimies of his Kingdome, as I have in diverſe books ſufficiently ſhewed, I ſay to ſpeake at this time of none of all theſe but onely of their preſent proceeding towards the King their Maſter, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Church and Common-wealth in generall, and all the poore people, and my ſelf in ſpeciall, you will quickly perceive that the Prelats are juſtly to be reputed among the worſt of men, and not amongſt the Nobles, for ought I know they and they onely are the cauſe of all the calamities in Church and State, which will manifeſtly appeare if wee looke ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the King or true Nobles, ſuch as love God, the King, their Country and Religion. And for the Kings moſt excellent Majeſties owne perſon, to ſpeake but that equity and juſtice require, what were ever any precedent Kings in this or any other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome renowned for, that is not in him, if you reſpect either vertues morall or theologicall, which are the onely honour of Princes, I ſay name any thing for piety, wiſdome, learning, proweſſe, temperance, cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, goodnes, bounty, affability, kindnes, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever els was in any other, do you not ſee it in him radically, nay doth he not ſeeme to be compoſed of goodnes? ſo that never was there any nation more happy in a King, then this our Nation is in ours. Againe to reflect our eye upon the whole ſecular Nobility either antient or moderne, I ſay to ſpeake of them in the generall, if you accoſt them, and by any occaſion have to deale with them, you ſhall find them ſo excellently inclined, and ſo favouring all vertue and goodnes, and of ſuch ſweet humanity and kindnes, and ſuch honourers and favourers of learning and true vertue, as they are exemplar to all other Nations; ſo that for King and Nobility no Nation or Kingdome can compare with ours, and yet nothwithſtanding all this, there is not in the world any Country that the ſubjects for the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality of them, groane under more preſſures, and are more tyrannically abuſed then amongſt us, if you reſpect either, bodies, ſoules or goods, having no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine liberty for a day of either, as woefull and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable experience hourely teacheth us. All which proceeds not either from the King who is goodnes it ſelf, and knoweth not how to doe evill, or from the Lords or Peeres of the Kingdom, who are like their King and Maſter, and fabricated of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity; from whence then I pray you proceed all the greivances of the poore people, but from the Prelats? who make a prey of the ſubject upon every triviall occaſion, and ſuggeſt into his royall eare both in publick and private ſtrange relations concerning them, as though they were the moſt diſloyall people unto his grace in the world, when I can upon my owne knowledge affirme that never King was more happy in a loyall and obedient people then the King is in them, never detrecting obedience to the loſſe of life liberty and eſtates, but as they were borne under obedience, deſire to live and dye in that condition, and are ever moſt willing to ſpend their beſt blouds for his honour, crowne and dignity, or in the cauſe of any of his allies, which is well knowen to the whole Chriſtian world. And yet notwithſtanding all this, their condition is moſt greivous, whether yea reſpect ſoule or body, liberty or meanes, they being every where deprived by the Prelats of their faithfull and true honorable Paſtors and diligent teachers, by which the keys of heaven are taken from them, and idle drones and Epicures put in their places, who neither feed the people themſelves with the bread of life, nor will let others doe it, or ſuffer them to provide for their owne ſoules good, but if they goe into any other pariſh to heare the word when they have none at home, then they hoyſt them up into the high Commiſſion, and there ruine and undoe them, or if the people for feare are deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from hearing of ſermons, and ſeeking to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the word of God, and if there chance a two or three neighbours to meet together for to conferre about holy things, or in every thing obſerve not all their vaine and needles, yea too too chargable and burdenſome Ceremonies, any of theſe things are matter enough to procure perdition and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto them of body, ſoule and goods, as daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience teacheth us. Neither can any ſecular man, Magiſtrat or Officer, be he Iuſtice of peace, Mayor, Bayly, or Conſtable, Iury-man, or witnes, or any other doe his office and duty in putting in execution the Kings Lawes, either for the honour of the King or his Religion againſt a delinquent Preiſt, or againſt any of their impious Officers, or write or witneſſe the truth againſt them or the common enimy, but they are immediatly hoiſted up in their Courts, and the King hath forthwith ſtrange informations gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven againſt them, as if they were notorious delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents againſt King, Church, and State, ſo that they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4725:5"/>are not onely deſerted of all help from his Majeſtie and Nobles, and the Lawes of his Kingdome, but made a prey to the mercileſſe fury of their enimies, and the Prelats being their enimies and parties, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Iury and Iudge in their owne cauſe, ſit and give ſentence againſt them. And whereas Chriſt would be no Iudge nor divider, they howſoever they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be his ſucceſſors, judge the poore people moſt cruelly, and divide not onely their inheritance, but give away their whole eſtates, and commit their ſoules to the Devill, and commit their bodies to eternall priſons to the utter undoing of them, their poore wives and children, and that upon every triviall occaſion, and many times againſt all Lawes of God and nature, and captivate the poore people, and keepe them in a greater ſlavery both for ſoule and body, then ever Pharao did. And whereas Chriſt came to heale &amp; cure, and ſpilt his owne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud for the redemption of others, and no ſooner was Malchus his eare cut off, but hee put it on againe, they ſpill the blood of the people, and cut off their eares at pleaſure, yea with ignorance and cruelty murder them, ſoules and bodies, of all which no ſubject can be ignorant, that knoweth any thing, and I by woefull experience have found it; ſo that for my particular, I may truely ſay that, in reſpect of our gracious King and his clemency, I had rather live with bread and water under his regiment, then in all plenty under any Prince in the world, yet in reſpect of the Prelats tyranny who abuſe the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity committed into their hands, I had rather live under the grand ſenior, in the meaneſt condition then where they domineer, with all plenty, for by their cruell proceedings &amp; curſed inhumanity, they ſo imbitter our lives, and make us ſo odious both in Court and Countrey, and ſuch a prey to every pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Preiſt, that our lives are not onely irkſome unto us, but our being and living a very burden, ſo that death is moſt welcome, for by that and that onely we are ſet at liberty. And I dare preſume, that of what I now ſay, ten thouſand thouſands will wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with mee of the truth of it: For it is the Prelats that have onely enſlaved us againſt all the Lawes of God and the Land, and have made us hatefull to all men, and a ſpectacle of men and Angels, and yet they perſwade his royall Majeſtie, that they are his moſt loyall and faithfulleſt ſubjects, and all thoſe they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for Puritans the peſt and plague of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſeek with Human the extirpation of them all. and by all manner of oppreſſions make thouſands of them fly the land, and others that have no abilities to ſupport them in ſtrange Countries to eate the bread of affliction, and live here with wounded con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, when they put upon them ſuch burdens of Popiſh Ceremonies, and force them upon payne of ſevere puniſhment to the obſervation of ſo many ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious performances, which by their knowledge and in their conſciences, they are taught ever to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre, and by this meanes the people are made miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable every kind of way. And all this intolerable bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage procedeth onely from the Prelats who many times arme themſelves with his Majeſties authority pretending to his Highnes, that they onely injoyne thoſe things for order, when there is no ſuch matter. And while they doe all this annoy to the kings ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, can they challenge the name of Mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>es, and be counted among the truely noble Peeres of the Kingdome, eſpecially, when in their open Courts they renounce his authority, and challenge their owne preeminency and dignity <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his ſubjects for writing againſt Antichriſt and the Church of Rome, which King Iames calls Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon and Spirituall Egypt and Sodome, to the infinit diſhonour of King Iames of famous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the now King their Maſter? by all which procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings they have made themſelves guilty of great contumacy againſt God and the King, and <hi>ipſo facto</hi> are all in a Premunire. by which they are fallen from all honour and dignity: and are at the Kings mercy as delinquents, and ſuch as for my part, ſo long as they continue in that condition, I never intend to honour. Neither have I cauſe for my owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to think any otherwiſe of them, then of n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cent members of Church and State, both by the warrant of King Iames himſelf, and for their carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards mee and the Kings beſt ſubjects: for when I was in the high Commiſſion Court, how ſuperci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liouſly the Prelats carried themſelves towards mee all the ſtanders by can tell: and when the advocats ſaw the violence of his deportment towards mee, and earneſtly perſwaded mee to an humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, for otherwiſe they told mee he would ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly undoe mee which indeed ſo fell out. I then replying that I was not conſcious to my ſelf of any delinquency either againſt God or the King, or that deſerved convention before any Court of Iudicature in the world, and for my part I reſolved to dye rather then by baſeneſſe of ſubmiſſion to make my ſelf an offender. Vpon which they demanded of mee if I would contend with their Lords grace, I then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine anſwered, that I contended with no man, but for the truth of God, and the honour of the King, my Country and Religion, and in that contention I would live &amp; dye. Whereupon one of the cheifeſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vocats in v court told me, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prelat would kill me with his breath, which I conſes was ſuch a diabolicall expreſſion, and a ſpeech of ſuch arrogancy, as never I thinke before was heard of: and therefore upon that, I called him ever after <hi>VVilliam the Dragon,</hi> for the Dragon onely killeth men with his breath as Hiſtorians do relate, and as the Apocalips witneſſeth, and had I not been a Phyſitian, and had an Antidote againſt it, what do you thinke would have become of mee, when his breath is poyſon? I muſt inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly confeſſe it, I thinke it is not ſafe that ſuch a breath ſhould come nigh the King, &amp; who knowes but that he was the cauſe of this laſt yeares plague
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4725:6"/>that killed ſo many, and that hee infected the ayre. And for the Prelat of York, he would have had mee knocked downe with club law, for maintaining the Kings prerogative royall againſt Papall uſurpation, and ſaid in open Court that hee was not beholding to the King for his Biſhoprick, for Ieſus Chriſt made him a Biſhop, and the Holy Ghoſt conſecrated him, when notwithſtanding he never performed the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Biſhop and true Paſtor of Ieſus Chriſt, but hath ever been a meere drone, and a hinderer of all preaching and teaching by all which he may well deſerve cenſure from the King and State, as being in a Premunire, and the title of an abby lubber. But you ſay, they are privy Councellors, and that the Angell would not revile the Devill, and therefore I have done amiſſe in that. To all which I will breifly anſwer and ſo conclude, as concerning their digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo long as they had not by their miſdemeanour made themſelves delinquents. I never impeached it or hurt their renowne in the leaſt, but they falling from grace &amp; becoming contumacious againſt God and the King, and noyſome to all his poore ſubjects, in this condition where now they are, I conceive no honour due unto them, nor they worthy of any dignity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they acknowledge their errors, &amp; crave pardon of God and his moſt Sacred Majeſtie. And the truth is, it is great pitty, that there is none of the Nobles that will informe his Highnes of their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, by which they have made themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of all honour, much leſſe to be of his privy Councell and moſt ſecret admiſſion, they are the privy members of the Clergy that ſtand up againſt all goodnes and adulterate the whole Church. And what miſcheife may not ſuch men doe, who have abandoned all good conſcience nay what miſery have they not brought all the Kings ſubjects into? For they when they are moſt diſloyall and pernicious to Church and State: yet make the King beleeve that they are his beſt ſubjects, and the ſupport of his Crowne and Dignity, and the onely upholders of Government, &amp; thus they prate alſo in open Courts: and this hath ever been the language of Antichriſt and his limbs, No Pope, no Church, No Pope, no King, but preſent confuſion upon all Nations where his Government is called in queſtion: when as it is well knowne to all thoſe that are not ſtrangers to the Hiſtories of times, that the Biſhops of Rome haue made Kings and Emperors their very Vaſſalls, and have been the bane of many floriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: and to this day inſlave all thoſe Chriſtian Princes, and their ſubjects where ever I ſay, they have power and authority, ſo that the Kings have onely the name, but they command, and their Cardinalls Preiſts and Prelats, and are attended like Princes, their very meat being ſtood bare to as to Kings. For they ſay, Be uncovered my Lords meat is comming up, ſo that they captivate Princes, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Lords, Neither can it be otherwiſe: for they have the breeding of all thoſe Kings &amp; Princes: and they are reſolved to keepe them in a perpetuall igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: for they ſay that King Henries and King Iames his learning was the overthrow of the church, and ſo long as Princes and Kings were kept in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes they then held their poſſeſſions and honours in all ſecurity: but ſince that they began to looke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed into learning, they found it fatall to them, &amp; therefore, they have now decreed amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves hereafter, that Princes and Nobles which they will have the breeding of, ſhall be acquainted with nothing but pleaſures, or at moſt with Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall learning, Nay they ſhall be perſwaded, it is rather a diſhonour to a King to know letters, then a dignity, and that it is not fit for them to looke on a booke, it being enough for Kings to have learned men in their Kingdome: and a floriſhing clergie, neither is it for them to trouble themſelves about learning or religion, but to leave it to the reverend Fathers, and to put their authority into their hands, and they will caſe them of all cares that way, ſo that they ſhall in time find a ſweet content, for they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to make them a people ſubject enough which indeed they doe, for they make them beggers and ſlaves, and moſt Kings that they have the tutoring of, either children or tyrants, and all the Nations where they have place but an unhappy people, for they keepe them ignorant, and deprive them of the liberty of their conſciences, and take away the right of the ſubjects from them. For all the Kingdome of Antichriſt is a monſtrous deformity of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſuch as advanceth it ſelf above all that is called God: and tramples upon all ſtates of men, ſo that it is a wonder to mee that all the Kings and Princes in the world do not joyne together to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſh that Babell, and to ruine the whore. But I much more admire, that in this Kingdome where there is ſo much light, &amp; ſo underſtanding a Prince, that the Nobles and Gentry with the Commons do not joyne together to petition his Majeſtie, that we may be eaſed of this intolerable yoake of theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats that are now by their frequent uſurpations, eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of his royall prerogative, moſt burdenſome to his poore ſubjects, and if there be not ſome ſpeedy courſe taken with them will ruine this floriſhing Monarchy. All which is ſo palpable as all men that ſee any thing in States affaires may eaſily behold it.</p>
            <p>There is one thing, that I cannot but ſtand aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at, that ſo many wiſe men in a Kingdome ſhould not looke into, and perceive the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of it, and the wrong it doth to the whole Nation, and that is this. That the breeding of the Kings and Noblemens childeren, and the moſt il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Families through the Kingdome, ſhould be put into the hands of Preiſts; and ſuch men who as they are by nature and education men that never ſaw farther then a Cloiſter at Cambridg or Oxford, never knew what Heroicall and Princely vertue was,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4725:6"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> never came where either breeding religion, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d maners came: the Vniverſities themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing corrupted by them and, and educated to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſtition or prophaneſſe, and contempt of religion. And yet notwithſtanding theſe men I ſay, ſhould be made the tutors of Kings and Nobles children, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght to be brought up by learned and truely reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Gentlemen that have been bred up in Princes Courts, and are lovers of learning, piety, and vertue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all which thoſe monkiſh fellowes are meere ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rs, and are as fit to bring up Princes, as a cow is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſaddle: for beſides their deficiencies both na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>all and morall, they are a very ignorant ſociety for the moſt part, not knowing well themſelves or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary literature, ſo that they are commonly ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lous to other Nation, I muſt confeſſe, I thinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his to be one of the principall banes of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ity, and that they know no more in learning and States policy which is their art; and therefore if they will follow a poore mans counſell, I would wiſh them all, never to let a Preiſt or a Prelat breed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir children: for all the Prelats and Preiſts are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>bs of the beaſt and his image, and they bring up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Noblemen and Princes in the hatred of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igion, and all them that feare the Lord, and brand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with Puritaniſme and adapt them onely to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itious obſervations, and make them beleeve that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e hath religion enough that can bow at the name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f Ieſus, or crouch to the Altar, or turne to the Eaſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d doe ſuch other performances, with hearing of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ttle ſervice: and that all thoſe that are not affected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith this ſuperſtition, are enimies of Church and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ute: and ſo they make theſe worthy heroes, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir executioners and butchers to torment and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ict the poore people whereſoever they have power. The truth is, The Prelats are the curſed enimies of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lord Ieſus Chriſt and his Kingdome, neither is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> any rayling to call a ſpade a ſpade, the Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alls their predeceſſors the Scribes, Phariſies, and High Preiſts, a generation of vipers, the Sonnes of the Devill, &amp;c. and therefore by the ſame autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, wee may call them by the ſame names, for they are their ſucceſſors and the of-ſpring of Antichriſt, who is the enimy of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and by conſequent no lawfull authority, but an uſurping power, that is, an enimy to all Government appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God himſelf: and therefore they are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of thoſe Saint Iude ſpeaketh of: being worſe then Satan, who when he was there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked, let the Angell bury Moſes, but the Biſhop of Rome will keepe whole Kingdomes from buriall ſix yeares together, and the Prelats have the ſame power to doe the ſame wickednes, yea they are not onely not ſo obedient to God as the Devill, but they are greater cauſes of rebellion againſt God, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore worſe, then the Devill, and ought more to be deteſted: for the Devill, in tempting to ſin and bringing me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to evill, he hath buth a ſimple ſuggeſtion: But the Prelats they have a double power, for they can both ſuggeſt evill, and conſtraine us to doe it, as all Kingdomes &amp; Nations know very well, who groane under the heavy burden of their unſupportable ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny; and therefore I do abſolutly conclude, that there is no ſinne in ſaying, <hi>the Prelats are the little toes of Antichriſt,</hi> and in calling, <hi>the Pope of Canterbury VVILLIAM the DRAGON,</hi> and his <hi>Legatus a latere. the Bishop of Yorke, the ABBEY LVBBER OF THE NORTH,</hi> for they are enimies all of God and the King, and of all the Saints and Servants of God. And therefore to draw now to a concluſion, I could wiſh that all the world in our <hi>dayly LETANY would pray with mee, from plague, pestilence, and famin, from Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops, Preiſts, and Deacons, Good Lord deliver us.</hi> Fare you well.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours moſt infettered <hi>In Lymbo Patrum</hi> IOHN BASTWICK.</signed>

Heare ends the fourth part of my LETANY, the other foure are to follow, as alſo ſome of my Latine books are shortly to come out.</closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nihil agunt Epiſcopi, ſine typho ſacriligae ſuperbia, ſine inflata cervice arrogantiae, ſine contentione lividae invidiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> aſancta humilitate, a pace Catholica, a charitate Chriſtiana,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Biſhops do nothing without the haughtines of ſacrilegious pride, without the ſwollen necke of arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cie, without the contention of wan envy, far from holy humility, from Catholicke peace, from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ian charity.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
